the criteria for induction into the
cleveland international hall of fame is
for someone who has made a significant
and lasting contribution to one or more
ethnic groups or the entire ethnic
community as a whole
architect burr shakarian fits this
definition to a t
since 2010 sold out crowds of 500 or
more have gathered annually to honor new
inductees into the cleveland
international hall of fame and be
inspired by their achievements and words
unfortunately this came to an abrupt
stop in 2020 when coven 19 prevented
groups from gathering
the 2020 class had already been selected
from a worthy list of over 100 nominees
but we could not gather together to
honor them
until we can gather together again we
are inducting the 2020 class virtually
it's not the same and they deserve the
applause of 500 people in the room but
at least they will be recognized as you
will hear in the following induction
speeches burst shakirian is a member of
the armenian community and a world-class
architect
his work in the armenian cultural garden
especially on the stunning armenian
alphabet sculpture is certainly
significant and lasting
the cleveland armenian community
clergy dignitaries and friends gathered
at the new armenian cultural garden at
741 mlk boulevard in cleveland on sunday
september 19 2010.
the alphabet monument symbolizes the
centrality of the armenian language in
creating the armenian state
in order to make the bible accessible to
armenians saint mezrab
invented the alphabet around 404 ce
the alphabet sculpture is composed of
staggered granite blocks representing
both the turbulent history of the
armenian people and the ruggedly
beautiful landscape of armenia and the
caucasus region
the reverse side of the monument is
inscribed with pride of a nation listing
the anglicized names of 33 men and women
noted for their historical and cultural
contributions to the armenian nation as
briefly stated next to each name
significant and lasting especially to
the armenian community
but birds do not stop there
as architect of the centennial peace
plaza in the cleveland cultural gardens
burj helped create a gathering space for
music dance entertainment and more for
generations to come
anyone driving down mlk boulevard can
witness two of the significant and
lasting creations of 2020 cleveland
international hall of fame inductee
burshakarian
congratulations bird
i'm wild curry the president of the
cleveland cultural gardens federation
i want to congratulate mr burshakarian
for being inducted to the international
hall of fame in cleveland
i've known berge for many many years and
i always find him a
very professional person very diligent
in his work
always seek
perfection in his designs and
construction
and he was very instrumental in
building up the armenian cultural garden
and in the last three four years i
worked very closely with him to
build up the centennial peace plaza he
made the designs
and he did the best job possible for an
architect
to get this beautiful plaza here
up to par with the best uh
best
features
or monuments in cleveland
so we're very excited uh that burj was
able to do this
and we wish him and his family
best wishes for good health for many
years to come
thank you hello
my name is paul burick
i'm the past recipient of this
prestigious award it is my privilege an
honor to introduce to you my friend and
colleague berkshire kerry
bridge is the architect of this new
feature in a cleveland cultural garden
the centennial peace plaza
how appropriate
that mr shakarian
would be inducted into the cleveland
international hall of fame
at one of his own designs
to us architects
utilization of our creation is the most
sincere formal reward
bridge shakirian cherishes his armenian
heritage
although
he was born and grew up in bucharest
romania
as with many refugee families
the path to safety and success is small
and winding
as a young boy in bucharest burch
enjoyed chess
sketching buildings
and soccer
bridge
told me a story from his youth
that qualified all these
three quantities to his future
as a boy he obtained two
excuse me
as a boy he obtained two tickets to an
important soccer match and
was all excited to see a premier team
play in the international soccer match
however
his mother
made him give up the tickets to his
sister so that she could go on a date
despite a huge disappointment
he obliged
and gave up his cherished pair of
tickets
not giving up on his on seeing the game
bridge managed to sneak into the game
who would stop
who would stop an eight-year-old boy who
appeared to be lost
at the game he met his sister
and her dad
who happened to be a young architect
with his sharp reasoning developing
chess
and the love of catching buildings and
inspired by his new acquaintance
bridge destiny was cast
he needed to be an architect
burchikarian arrived in america on july
4th
and there were fireworks everywhere
yes it was 60 years ago this month
he enrolled at case western reserve
university
to study architecture
commuting to classes
he met his future wife on rapid transit
of all places he and carol
american of hungarian heritage
went in 1971.
that makes a 50-year anniversary this
year congratulations on that virgin
carol
they brought up four children
all
now hold phds of course
they are very proud of them
though bridge did mention that none of
them became an architect
after private practice of architecture
for three years
mr shakarian
was invited to be a cuyahoga county
architect
what a achievement
at the 32-year career with the county
berks retired
although he still teaches and does
occasional work mainly for the new
gardens here in this beautiful park
he participated in the restoration of
the lakeside excuse me lakeside
courthouse a landmark building
as well as refurbishing of the soldiers
and sailors monument
at the public square what an honor
mr shakarian oversaw numerous
building upgrades and new construction
for the county
as i already noted mr shakarian is the
architect
for this plaza
he also
designed the armenian cultural garden
and is currently helping the turkish
community with their new garden
for those of you who are aware of the
recent history and attention in that
region
it is absolutely admirable
that mr shakaryan would rise above it
all for the sake of friendship
and mutual understanding the motto of
these spectacular cultural regards
and that is purge
bridge
it is my pleasure to present to you the
cleveland international hall of fame
trophy
and it is a
tradition to paint a new inductee with a
pen
[Applause]
welcome to the
group thank you
okay
thank you paul burek
and my sincere gratitude to the entire
hall of fame committee for selecting me
to join such a prestigious company
i am both honored and humbled during
these trying times
it was the best of times it was the
worst of times
it was the year of 2020.
cleveland has been a journey of
discovery for me for almost 60 years
this town has become the place that i
call home
and have created a family life with a
lovely local hungarian girl
[Applause]
we met on the old cts rapid transit
while commuting to college
and since that time we have had four
children
in 50 years together
as a young man wandering the streets of
downtown cleveland
i came to love this city passionately
know that i know that one day i would be
responsible for restoring and repairing
the imposing soldiers and sailors
monuments
oh that i would have a hand in saving
the state and ohio theaters
i recall
walking in the state theater
with the roof collapsing
and seeing
the east of java movie poster with
robert mitchum
today
playhouse square is certainly a success
story
cleveland has changed for the better
and occasionally in some ways
not for the better
however
today
we still admire the vision of mayor
tamil johnson and his legacy
which was to make cleveland a
progressive city
that evolved from a village to a great
american metropolis
during those first decades after turn of
the century
cleveland suddenly
became the biggest city
between new york and chicago
the progressive vision attracted much
talent to cleveland
one such individual was robert moses
at the time moses was not welcome to
cleveland
he went and he went on to become
the controversial parks commissioner in
the state of new york changing new york
city from a medieval town to a modern
metropolis
how might have
cleveland change if he had remained here
as an architect
i marvel at the civic buildings clouding
stone and defining the mall for the
meaning and value
this new structure cladding glass and
metal never quite had a gravitas
glass and metal buildings get during
time while
stone buildings age gracefully
with a patina
filled with memories
like old wine
i too was blessed to have a hand in
mayor tunnel johnson's vision
by restoring the crown jewel of the
brook plant
the kaihara county courthouse
it has been
a lifetime endeavor and well worth the
effort
however
cleveland has lots of well-kept secrets
those secrets are the cleveland cultural
gardens
and now they are becoming less and less
a secret
it was the dedication of the
shakespearean garden in 1916
and the inspiration of leo wyden powell
that provided for this gardens of peace
to encourage the local population
for a better world
[Applause]
thus the cleveland cultural gardens were
founded over 100 years ago
set in the beautiful rockefeller park
between lake erie and university circle
the gardens include monuments and
memorials
that represent more than 30
nationalities
it is a cosmopolitan landmark unlike any
in the world that promotes peace and
understanding among different cultures
on a personal note in this context that
our son pietro
insisted on the creation of the armenian
cultural garden in 2008.
pietro recently earned a phd from ohio
state university
the cleveland connection exists here as
well
his thesis centers on a anastasia
the soviet states when he came to
cleveland in 1959
to visit cyrus eaton
on 21st of august 2020
the cleveland cultural gardens
federation
celebrated the virtual dedication
of the centennial peace plaza with a
score from anthony devorak
congratulations to all the gardens
the plaza shall serve as a setting for
memory
meaning reflection and community with an
average peace to mutual understanding
it is a fine opportunity to increase
awareness
of our cultural heritage as americans
and to create a wonderful teaching
moment
for the community at large
the effort is dedicated
to the people of the world who suffer
during
2020 covert 19 pandemic
once again
many thanks for this special
thank you